<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rachit Nigam on Rachit Nigam</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rachit Nigam on Rachit Nigam</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Rachit Nigam 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How I flipped a coin to decide on my grad school</title>
      <link>/post/grad-school-decision/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 23:53:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/grad-school-decision/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;So you &lt;a href=&#34;http://jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2011/12/reasons-to-pursue-phd.html&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;decided to do a PhD&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2012/10/faq-applying-to-graduate-school-for.html&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;applied to a few schools&lt;/a&gt;, and visited schools you got accepted to now. Now comes
the hard part of the process: deciding which school you&amp;rsquo;re going to spend the
next 5+ years at. While I cannot provide a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sigplan.org/Resources/EmpiricalEvaluation/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;checklist&lt;/a&gt; or a simple answer, I can talk about my experience
when deciding on which school I should go to and a few questions that I answered
while making that decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title is &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; clickbait. However, in my case, it was not untrue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-are-you-doing-a-phd&#34;&gt;Why are you doing a PhD?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my first interview during admission period, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ccs.neu.edu/~matthias/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Matthias Felleisen&lt;/a&gt; asked me &amp;ldquo;Why do you want to do a PhD?&amp;rdquo; While simple,
superficial answers such as &amp;ldquo;I like learning new things&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;I enjoy research&amp;rdquo;, or
&amp;ldquo;I want &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; job&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; usually suffice in interview settings, they do not
help with profound life decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my decision, answers 1 and 3 pulled me in two different directions. Between
my choices, A, B, and C, I felt that going to school A might maximize my chances
of getting an academic job while going to B or C would maximize my ability to
learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, answer 1 won out and choose to go to Cornell because I felt it
had &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~asampson/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;cool&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cornell.edu/~jnfoster/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;people&lt;/a&gt; who &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cornell.edu/~kozen/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;enjoy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.cornell.edu/andru/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;programming&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cornell.edu/~jgm/jgm.html&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;languages&lt;/a&gt; research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;are-the-grad-students-happy&#34;&gt;Are the grad students happy?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the primary reason I chose Cornell over other schools. All my choices
were good technical fits, but graduate students at Cornell seemed content with
what they were doing. Cornell&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;./post/free-agent-cornell&#34;&gt;free agent system&lt;/a&gt;
initially turned me off because I was terrified of not finding an advisor.
However (as the above linked post mentions), this concern was ill founded and
I started working with my current advisor within a week of joining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-friends&#34;&gt;On friends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My good friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://samginzburg.com/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Sam Ginzburg&lt;/a&gt; helped me out a lot
with the decision process. Having a peer to talk to about graduate school
decisions can be incredibly helpful since they are not invested in recruiting
you to a particular school and might provide some objective insights about
your own thought processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest argument that both my Mom and Sam made that help me make a decision
was, &amp;ldquo;the worst case is that you end up not enjoying and transfer to one of
your other choices&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-coins&#34;&gt;On coins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in fact true that I flipped a coin to make a decision about my graduate
school. However, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the coin flip that convinced me to go to a particular
school; it was the fact that I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to flip the coin again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-decisions&#34;&gt;On decisions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I will end with this quote from my undergraduate advisor&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://repository.library.brown.edu/studio/item/bdr:297608/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dissertation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a particularly trying time, Joe observedthat “Some decisions in life are so important, like picking a career or a spouse, but you can’t iterateuntil you make the right decision, so you just have to do it,” and thus inspired me to press on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graduate school decisions might seem hard and the processes seem random. Perhaps,
a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leap_of_faith#Kierkegaard,_Goethe,_Marx,_and_Tolstoy&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;leap of faith&lt;/a&gt; is the only right choice we can make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have comments? &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:rachit.nigam12@gmail.com&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Email&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/notypes&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; at me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;This is the answer I gave to &lt;a href=&#34;https://emeryberger.com/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Emery Berger&lt;/a&gt; when he asked me the same question.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Reading the &amp;ldquo;Acknowledgements&amp;rdquo; sections in PhD dissertations is a preferred pass time of mine.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Management for PhD Students</title>
      <link>/post/project-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2019 22:10:39 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/project-management/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Collaborations in systems research is how I&amp;rsquo;ve built some of the best tools
in my research. A larger teams means an expanded vision and being able to pursue more
ambitious ideas but it also incurs an overhead &amp;ndash; team management. Effectively
managing a team and keeping all team members up to date can be stressful and a
daunting task. I think one way to approaching management tasks is by asking
a few concrete questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the primary channel of communication?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How often should we be meeting? What are the preparing expectations for a meeting?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are we managing our code base? What are the expectations about code knowledge?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are we managing our TODO items?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How should we resolve conflicts?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answers to these questions should evolve with a project. For example, a
project in its prototyping stage might have no restrictions on how or where the
code is kept but a more mature project associated with other projects or
deployments requires careful releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following sections answer these questions from my experience with teams.
The answers apply for a reasonably mature project with most core infrastructure
decisions already made (which language to use, which toolchains, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I&amp;rsquo;m not the most experienced developer in the world, I would appreciate any suggestions (find my contact information at the end of the post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;primary-communication&#34;&gt;Primary Communication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an easy one. Teams can either use email threads or one of the dozens
of chat applications to have conversations about the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefit of using a emails is that the team can keep track of individual
threads of conversations easily. However, with multiple projects, this might
get unwieldy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chat apps, on the other hand, make it really quick and easy to communicate with
the team but are usually bad at maintaining separate threads of conversations
cleanly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of the primary communication is often already constrained by group
preferences so this is usually a straightforward decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a side note, team members should try to have long conversations in person.
Text based mediums make it really hard to accurately convey emotions and it
is easy to misread an offhand comment as being aggressive (I&amp;rsquo;ve certainly been
guilty of this!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;meetings&#34;&gt;Meetings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meetings act as a synchronization point for the entire team and require some amount
of preparation. I suggest having at least two team meetings every week, one
with your advisor (main meeting) and one without them (student meeting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;main-meeting&#34;&gt;Main meeting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the main meeting, every student should be prepared with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A short weekly update.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical challenges faced during the assigned task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Questions or gotchas found during the assigned the task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the main meeting, each student should leave with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least one assigned task for the week. This can be a paper to read and explain, feature to implement, or a theorem to prove.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A good sense of where to look for answers to their questions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of students (myself included) struggle with prioritizing tasks. Students
involved in research have tons of unstructured time which is not utilized
effectively without a good plan. Assigned tasks help me focus on a task that
I need to get done every week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concretely, I try every week to either complete the tasks assigned to me or
have technical questions that are blocking me ready for the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;student-meeting&#34;&gt;Student meeting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The student meetings are more informal and are meant for in depth discussions
about small issues that team members are facing in completing their tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;codebases&#34;&gt;Codebases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re working on an applied systems project chances are you are building
a software artifact. Regardless of how many people are writing code, it is useful to
check in the code into &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Version_control&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;source
control&lt;/a&gt;. This makes the code
publicly viewable and commentable by the team members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high-level principle behind these guidelines is to minimize the number of locations where critical information such as feature discussions are kept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I primarily use &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rachitnigam&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;, the following guidelines assume your
project is Github-based. When working on a artifact, I have the following
expectations with team members:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The project leaders (graduate students or senior undergrads) should have a
good sense of what is going on with every aspect of the codebase. This means
having a high-level understanding of all pull requests and issue discussions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/articles/about-pull-requests&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pull requests&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/articles/about-branches&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;branches&lt;/a&gt;. Working
on big features on a separate branch allows other people to work in parallel
while leaving the code in a buildable state. Pull requests are a great way
to get the team&amp;rsquo;s attention on a big change and center discussions around it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the git history clean by using &lt;code&gt;git pull -r&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/articles/about-git-rebase&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rebasing&lt;/a&gt; instead of
merging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;todo-list&#34;&gt;TODO List&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since most of my projects revolve around a software artifact, most of which
are on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rachitnigam&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;, I use Github issues as
a tracking list. Other people I have worked with also use &lt;a href=&#34;https://trello.com/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; or one of the dozens of TODO apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The todo list should make it easy to create tasks and have discussions around them and also allow team members to see who is working on what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the development phase of the project, I ask the team to use
issues liberally. The term &amp;ldquo;global tracker&amp;rdquo; refers to the high level view of
all todo items. On Github, this is simply the issues page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Largely, I divide issues into three categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trackers&lt;/strong&gt;. Trackers are a collection of smaller issues that logically belong
together but might pollute the global tracker. Use these for reading lists,
benchmark status, and low priority tasks. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cucapra/seashell/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;q=is%3Aissue+label%3ATracker+&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Example&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposal&lt;/strong&gt;. Proposal are the heart of the global tracker. Use proposals to
discuss system features, implementation sketches, or big bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/strong&gt;: These include questions or small bugs. These should be
high frequency, i.e. created liberally, and answered quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conflict-resolution&#34;&gt;Conflict resolution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an often overlooked dimension of team dynamics. Research projects can
often be stressful, especially since students tend to be ambitious and prone
to overworking. Since this process so highly dependent on the team members
and project leads, my guideline can only be personalized for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a team member feels under too much pressure to do something or dislikes
someone&amp;rsquo;s personal behavior, they can either directly contact the person or
ask one of the team leads to mediate. While daunting, it is much better in the
long run to have frank discussions about team expectations and stresses instead
of letting things get worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are several industrial strength methodologies for team managements,
I like having a much more lightweight team management style. A lot of research
is about exploring new ideas and pursuing crazy ideas. Regardless of which
guidelines you choose to follow, they should not take away the joy of programming
or research!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussion on &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19321034&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;HackerNews&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have comments? &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:rachit.nigam12@gmail.com&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Email&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/notypes&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; at me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Fail</title>
      <link>/post/learn-to-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 07:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/learn-to-fail/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I often describe the basic philosphy of research using a metaphor.  I find
research to be like head bashing a wall over and over till you find a way to
break it and then repeating it ad nauseam.  Sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll know where the
cracks in the wall are, and sometime you&amp;rsquo;ll know what angle you need to hit the
wall with your head, but fundamentally, you&amp;rsquo;re hitting your head into a wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might not be a precise description of how research works for everyone, but
my views are shaped by my experience at research and other researchers who
surround me. The single most important take away I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from these is
to expect failure and to work hard regardless. These two things are not always
easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate my viewpoint, and to demonstrate how I became such a tortured
soul, here&amp;rsquo;s a run down of my experience as an undergraduate researcher:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;spring-2016&#34;&gt;Spring 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reached out a my undergraduate advisor in my first semester after being
fascinated with scheme &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. After some back and forth, I quickly started
a project. The project was to build a formal semantics for bash scripts. The
bash specification is large and complicated with a lot of subtle interactions.
The particular phase we were interested in formalizing were the bash shell
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/bash/manual/html_node/Shell-Expansions.html&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;expansions&lt;/a&gt;. We tried to build a Hoare logic style semantics for the expansion, because
we wanted to ultimately verify properties of these shell scripts. Unfortunately,
I showed that such a semantics becomes super complicated and we abandoned the
project &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. A few weeks into research and I had already failed a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;summer-2016&#34;&gt;Summer 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came back for the summer and started working on a new, and slightly related
project. The idea was to extend previous work on &lt;a href=&#34;https://people.cs.umass.edu/~arjun/papers/2016-rehearsal.html&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;verifying Puppet
manifests&lt;/a&gt; to
capture the semantics of snippets of shell programs people write into their
Puppet manifests. The previous work had modeled Puppet programs using a
small core calculus based on a Kleene Algebra with Tests (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~kozen/Papers/kat.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;KAT&lt;/a&gt;) and we wanted to create an active learning
mechanism to learn the underlying automaton by running the shell script in
a docker container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of background in either automata theory or
the low level details of system call tracing (which was the core mechanism to
figure out what system calls were being used). I spent half of the summer
jumping back and forth between learning about automata theory and systems and
implementing papers without much to show for it. While I didn&amp;rsquo;t know this
at the time, this project also fizzled out around this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason the project fizzled out was because I joined another students
project that had to do with automatically synthesizing updates for Puppet
manifests by capturing system calls &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I worked on this project for the rest
of the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;fall-2016&#34;&gt;Fall 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the summer ended, my advisor proposed joining Fission, another project that
I had been interested in from the start of my summer. This project aimed to
build a single-tiered, secure programming model for writing web applications.
People on the project had built a frontend that could take JavaScript code and
compile it into something that could enforces security conditions.
Around the same time, the Puppet synthesis project slowed down because the
first author was applying to graduate schools and I was focusing more on
Fission.  Eventually, I stopped working on this project entirely and even
though it was eventually published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cap off the depressing string of half completed projects, it was around this
time I actually had minor clinical depression and my productivity collapsed. After
attending &lt;a href=&#34;https://conf.researchr.org/home/icfp-2016&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ICFP &amp;lsquo;16&lt;/a&gt; I decided to
start therapy to &amp;ldquo;fix&amp;rdquo; my clinical depression &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we also published a &lt;a href=&#34;http://drops.dagstuhl.de/opus/volltexte/2017/7124/pdf/LIPIcs-SNAPL-2017-5.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;workshop
paper&lt;/a&gt;
on Fission. Unfortunately, after several rewrites of the compiler, people
leaving the project, and fundamental performance issues, it was becoming
painfully clear that Fission would not pan out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not keeping track, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; for failed projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;spring-2017&#34;&gt;Spring 2017&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While making slow progress on Fission, my advisor asked a new question, &amp;ldquo;What
would it take to build a client-side IDE?&amp;ldquo;. In order to build this IDE, we
started investigating different compiler frameworks for JavaScript. We built
multiple passes to simplify JavaScript constructs and around the same time, another
graduate student joined the project. This spring was perhaps the most productive
semester of my undergraduate research career. I had gained enough technical
and programming chops to push on the project without hands-on support. By the
end of this semester, we had managed to build an IDE and give a talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;afterward&#34;&gt;Afterward&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept pushing on this project with the grad student and published a paper
in &lt;a href=&#34;https://conf.researchr.org/home/pldi-2018&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PLDI &amp;lsquo;18&lt;/a&gt;. I also applied to
graduate schools and decided to start my PhD at Cornell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, there are several important things I came to appreciate about
my undergraduate research:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;While I failed for more than a year, I learned &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;. The finite model
theory I learned in my first summer is seeing use in my current research. The
amount of implementation work I did made me good at rapid prototyping and
debugging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The infectious optimism of my advisor kept me going through all the failures.
In hindsight, perhaps the most important piece of advice he gave me was,
&amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;ll figure it out!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another thing I learned from my advisor was that sticking to a research agenda,
even when things look absymal, is the way to make progress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, I learned that researchers are completely unproductive when they&amp;rsquo;re sad.
Concretely, this means that I shy away from projects where I&amp;rsquo;m the only student.
Surrounding myself with people I like to work with and can bounce ideas with
is how I make progress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I summarized these ideas to a friend was that research sometimes
requires a religious amount of faith and hard work before you can see any progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have comments? &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:rachit.nigam12@gmail.com&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Email&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/notypes&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; at me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Yes, I am a walking PL cliché.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Michael Greenberg, one of our collaborators continued working on this and has come up with some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.pomona.edu/~michael/papers/px2018.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;nice results&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;This eventually became a &lt;a href=&#34;https://aaronweiss.us/pubs/ase17.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Researchers are people who sometimes work extraordinarily hard at the expense of their own health. It is important to realize that your work is significantly less important that your health.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD @ Cornell: The Free Agent system</title>
      <link>/post/free-agent-cornell/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 08:27:21 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/free-agent-cornell/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Deciding which graduate school you&amp;rsquo;re going to spend the next &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; years of your
life is one of the hardest decision of your life. One of the things
that made is hard for me was deciding between Cornell and my other
top choice was Cornell&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Free agent system&amp;rdquo;. Here is a short post about what
the system is and why it worked for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;graduate-school-admissions&#34;&gt;Graduate School Admissions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most schools in the US, when you apply to a PhD program, students are usually
picked out by one or more professors who think you&amp;rsquo;d be a good fit. After
visiting the school, the student decides which professor they want to work with
and commit to the school. When the student starts at the school, they are
funded by the professor and they start doing great things together. However,
some schools don&amp;rsquo;t follow this system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cornell-s-free-agent-system&#34;&gt;Cornell&amp;rsquo;s Free Agent System&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Cornell, and a few other schools, the admission process looks a bit
different.  When a PhD student is admitted to Cornell, they are are &lt;em&gt;admitted
to the department&lt;/em&gt;, which highlights Cornell&amp;rsquo;s commitment towards the student&amp;rsquo;s
academic freedom. Concretely, this means that Cornell guarantees funding,
usually through teaching assistantship, for the student without tying them to
an advisor [^1].  This is supposed to allow the students to explore and talk to
potential advisors without being worried about funding. This is the Free Agent
system at Cornell. Students are free agents till they decide who they want to
work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cornell&amp;rsquo;s free agent system was devised when the department was young and the
incoming PhD students tended to have comparatively less research experience.
The free agent system allowed students to explore different areas without
being pressured into working on topics they might disliked. However, in the recent
years, the makeup of people applying to PhD programs has drastically changed &amp;mdash;
students tend to come in with a lot more research experience and are usually
quite certain about the area they want to work in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the CS department is also structured in a way that assumes
students are free agents their first year. This means that they are expected to
&lt;del&gt;take a lot of classes and&lt;/del&gt; [^1] be teaching assistants (TAs) in their first
two semesters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;my-experience&#34;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The free agent system caused me a lot of angst during the decision process. For
some background, I had started doing programming languages (PL) research in the
first semester of my undergraduate degree and was certain about my future research
direction. Furthermore, I knew that Cornell was the best fit for my interest in
doing PL work at the intersection of other fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I was also afraid of not being able to find an advisor. After
about 6 hours of post visit day talks with professors and students in the PL
group, I decided to go to Cornell. Even after my acceptance, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure if
I&amp;rsquo;d be able to find an advisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started in Fall, I emailed professors in the PL group to set up
meetings. This is where I found the true strength of the free agent system.
Since professors expect students to go talk to a lot of people, they expect and
often encourage students to do research rotations with professors they are
interested in working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also makes it easy to reach out to professors and learn about their work. I
cannot emphasize how important it is to me to learn about and have
conversations about research in different domains. One of my goals going into a
PhD is to have a broad sense of the different kinds of problems in different
domains and having access to professors in different areas makes it easy to do
so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also able to start working with my awesome advisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~asampson/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Adrian
Sampson&lt;/a&gt; and we quickly found a project
I&amp;rsquo;m passionate about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;caveat-emptor&#34;&gt;Caveat Emptor&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the free agent system caused me some anguish in the decision process, it
was not the primary reason I decided join Cornell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My primary motivators were research that excited me, and people &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; who are
just as excited about it as me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first year TAing requirement causes some amount of stress for
new students. However, the department is aware of the issues and is
trying to move away from this system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here is a more &lt;a href=&#34;http://jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2009/02/some-notes-on-picking-grad.html&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;detailed
post&lt;/a&gt; from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://jeanyang.com/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jean Yang&lt;/a&gt; on what considerations matter when deciding
on schools. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have comments? &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:rachit.nigam12@gmail.com&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Email&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/notypes&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; at me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Importantly, This includes other grad students. Remember, you&amp;rsquo;re going to be spending a lot more time with other grad students than you will with faculty.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Putting in All the Stops</title>
      <link>/publication/stopify/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 15:39:56 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/stopify/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fission: Secure Dynamic Code-Splitting for JavaScript</title>
      <link>/publication/fission/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 17:19:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/fission/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
