<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rachit Nigam on Rachit Nigam</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rachit Nigam on Rachit Nigam</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Rachit Nigam 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Fail</title>
      <link>/post/learn-to-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 07:20:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/learn-to-fail/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The way I often describe research to my non-research friends is by an
uncessarily violent metaphor. I find research to be like head bashing a wall
over and over till you find a way to break it and then repeating it ad nauseam.
Sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll know where the cracks in the wall are, and sometime you&amp;rsquo;ll
know what angle you need to hit the wall with your head, but fundamentally,
you&amp;rsquo;re hitting your head into a wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might not be a precise description of how research works for everyone, but
my views are shaped by my experience at research and other researchers who
surround me. The single most important take away I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from these is
to expect failure and to work hard regardless. These two things are not always
easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate my viewpoint, and to demonstrate how I became such a tortured
soul, here&amp;rsquo;s a run down of my experience as an undergraduate researcher:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;spring-2016&#34;&gt;Spring 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reached out a my undergraduate advisor in my first semester after being
fascinated with scheme &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. After some back and forth, I quickly started
a project. The project was to build a formal semantics for bash scripts. The
bash specification is large and complicated with a lot of subtle interactions.
The particular phase we were interested in formalizing were the bash shell
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/bash/manual/html_node/Shell-Expansions.html&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;expansions&lt;/a&gt;. We tried to build a Hoare logic style semantics for the expansion, because
we wanted to ultimately verify properties of these shell scripts. Unfortunately,
I showed that such a semantics becomes super complicated and we abandoned the
project &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. A few weeks into research and I had already failed a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;summer-2016&#34;&gt;Summer 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came back for the summer and started working on a new, and slightly related
project. The idea was to extend previous work on &lt;a href=&#34;https://people.cs.umass.edu/~arjun/papers/2016-rehearsal.html&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;verifying Puppet
manifests&lt;/a&gt; to
capture the semantics of snippets of shell programs people write into their
Puppet manifests. The previous work had modeled Puppet programs using a
small core calculus based on a Kleene Algebra with Tests (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~kozen/Papers/kat.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;KAT&lt;/a&gt;) and we wanted to create an active learning
mechanism to learn the underlying automaton by running the shell script in
a docker container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of background in either automata theory or
the low level details of system call tracing (which was the core mechanism to
figure out what system calls were being used). I spent half of the summer
jumping back and forth between learning about automata theory and systems and
implementing papers without much to show for it. While I didn&amp;rsquo;t know this
at the time, this project also fizzled out around this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason the project fizzled out was because I joined another students
project that had to do with automatically synthesizing updates for Puppet
manifests by capturing system calls &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I worked on this project for the rest
of the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;fall-2016&#34;&gt;Fall 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the summer ended, my advisor proposed joining Fission, another project that
I had been interested in from the start of my summer. This project aimed to
build a single-tiered, secure programming model for writing web applications.
People on the project had built a frontend that could take JavaScript code and
compile it into something that could enforce the various security conditions.
Around the same time, the Puppet synthesis project slowed down because the
first author was applying to graduate schools and I was focusing more on
Fission.  Eventually, I stopped working on this project entirely and even
though it was eventually published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cap off the depressing string of half completed projects, it was around this
time I actually had minor clinical depression and my productivity collapsed. After
attending &lt;a href=&#34;https://conf.researchr.org/home/icfp-2016&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ICFP &amp;lsquo;16&lt;/a&gt; I decided to
start therapy to &amp;ldquo;fix&amp;rdquo; my clinical depression &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we also published a &lt;a href=&#34;http://drops.dagstuhl.de/opus/volltexte/2017/7124/pdf/LIPIcs-SNAPL-2017-5.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;workshop
paper&lt;/a&gt;
on Fission. Unfortunately, after several rewrites of the compiler, people
leaving the project, and fundamental performance issues, it was becoming
painfully clear that Fission would not pan out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not keeping track, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; for failed projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;spring-2017&#34;&gt;Spring 2017&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While making slow progress on Fission, my advisor asked a new question, &amp;ldquo;What
would it take to build a client-side IDE?&amp;ldquo;. In order to build this IDE, we
started investigating different compiler frameworks for JavaScript. We built
several passes to simplify JavaScript constructs and around the same time, another
graduate student joined the project. This spring was perhaps the most productive
semester of my undergraduate research career. I had gained enough technical
and programming chops to push on the project without hands-on support. By the
end of this semester, we had managed to build an IDE and give a talk about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;afterward&#34;&gt;Afterward&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept pushing on this project with the grad student and published a paper
in &lt;a href=&#34;https://conf.researchr.org/home/pldi-2018&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PLDI &amp;lsquo;18&lt;/a&gt;. I also applied to
graduate schools and decided to start my PhD at Cornell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, there are several important things I came to appreciate about
my undergraduate research:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;While I mostly failed for more than a year, I learned &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;. The finite model
theory I learned in my first summer is seeing use in my current research. The
amount of implementation work I did has allowed me to become good at rapid
prototyping for new ideas &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The infectious optimism of my advisor was the single most important thing that
kept me going through all the failures. In hindsight, perhaps the most important
piece of advice he gave me was, &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;ll figure it out!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another thing I learned from my advisor was that sticking to a research agenda,
even when things look absymal, is the way to make progress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, I learned that researchers are completely unproductive when they&amp;rsquo;re sad.
Concretely, this means that I shy away from projects where I&amp;rsquo;m the only student.
Surrounding myself with people I like to work with and can bounce ideas with
is how I make most of my progress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I recently summarized these ideas to a friend was that research sometimes
requires a religious amount of faith and hard work before you can actually
see any progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have comments? &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:rachit.nigam12@gmail.com&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Email me&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/notypes&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; at me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Yes, I am a walking PL cliché.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;Michael Greenberg, one of our collaborators continued working on this and has come up with some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.pomona.edu/~michael/papers/px2018.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;nice results&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;This eventually became a &lt;a href=&#34;https://aaronweiss.us/pubs/ase17.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Researchers are people who sometimes work extraordinarily hard at the expense of their own health. It is important to realize that your work is significantly less important that your health.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Differently put, it made me a 1337 h4x0r.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD @ Cornell: The Free Agent system</title>
      <link>/post/free-agent-cornell/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 08:27:21 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/free-agent-cornell/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Deciding which graduate school you&amp;rsquo;re going to spend the next &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; years of your
life is possibly one of the hardest decision of your life. One of the things
that made is particularly hard for me was deciding between Cornell and my other
top choice was Cornell&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Free agent system&amp;rdquo;. Here is a short post about what
the system is and why it worked for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;how-do-grad-schools-work&#34;&gt;How do grad schools work?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most schools in the US, when you apply to a PhD program, you are usually
picked out by one (or more) professors who think you&amp;rsquo;d be a good. After
visiting the school, one the student usually decides which professor they want
to start working with. When the student starts at the school, they are funded
by the professor and they start doing great things together. However, some
schools don&amp;rsquo;t follow this system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cornell-s-free-agent-system&#34;&gt;Cornell&amp;rsquo;s Free Agent System&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Cornell, and a few other schools, the admission process looks a bit
different.  When a PhD student is admitted to Cornell, they are told that they
are &lt;em&gt;admitted to the department&lt;/em&gt;, which is supposed to highlight Cornell&amp;rsquo;s
committment towards the student freedom. Concretely, this means that Cornell guarantees
funding for the student without tying them to an advisor &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for the first few
years. This is supposed to allow the students to explore and talk to potential
advisors without being worried about funding. This is the Free Agent system at
Cornell. Students are free agents till they decide who they want to work with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cornell&amp;rsquo;s free agent system was devised when the department was young and the
incoming PhD students tended to have comparatively less reserch experience.
The free agent system allowed students to explore different areas without
being pressured to work on topics they might not like. However, in the recent
years, the makeup of people applying to PhD programs has drastically changed &amp;mdash;
students tend to come in with a lot more research experience and are usually
pretty sure about the area they want to work in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the CS department is also structured in a way that assumes
students are free agents their first year. This means that they are expected to
&lt;del&gt;take a lot of classes and&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; be teaching assistants (TAs) in their first
two semesters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;my-experience&#34;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The free agent system was the biggest reason that caused me to delay my
decision.  For some background, I had started doing programming languages (PL)
research in the first semester of my undergraduate degree and was quite certain
about what kind of stuff I wanted to work on. Furthermore, I knew that Cornell
was the best fit for my interest in doing PL work at the intersection of other
fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I was also afraid of not being able to find an advisor and
wanted to choose a school where I knew I had an advisor. After about 6 hours
of post visit day talks with professors and students in the PL group, I decided
to go to Cornell. Even after my acceptance, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure if I&amp;rsquo;d be able to
find an advisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started in Fall, I emailed several professors in the PL group and setup
meetings. This is where I found the true strength of the free agent system.
Since professors expect students to go talk to a lot of people, they expect and
often encourage students to do rotations with people they might want to work
with. It also makes it easy to reach out to professors and learn about their
work. I cannot understate how important it is to me to learn about and have
conversations about different research. One of my goals going into a PhD is
to have a broad sense of the different kinds of problems in different domains
and having access to professors in different areas makes it very easy to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also able to start working with my awesome advisor &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~asampson/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Adrian
Sampson&lt;/a&gt; and we quickly found a project
I&amp;rsquo;m passionate about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;caveat-emptor&#34;&gt;Caveat Emptor&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the free agent system worked for me, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the biggest factor in my
decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the end of the day, having research that excites you and people &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; who are
as excited as you are is the single most important thing when you&amp;rsquo;re deciding
schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first year TA problem is non-trivial and causes some amount of stress for
new grad students. However, the department is aware of the issues and is
trying to move away from this system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here is a more &lt;a href=&#34;http://jxyzabc.blogspot.com/2009/02/some-notes-on-picking-grad.html&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;detailed
post&lt;/a&gt; from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://jeanyang.com/&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jean Yang&lt;/a&gt; on what considerations matter when deciding
on schools. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have comments? &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:rachit.nigam12@gmail.com&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Email me&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/notypes&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; at me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Being tied to an advisor is not always a bad thing. In fact, most people decide on an &lt;em&gt;advisor&lt;/em&gt; and not a &lt;em&gt;school&lt;/em&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;The CS department recently overhauled the course requirement to drastically reduce the number of classes and restrictions on which classes to take.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;Importantly, This includes other grad students. Remember, you&amp;rsquo;re going to be spending a lot more time with other grad students than you will with faculty.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;↩&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Putting in All the Stops</title>
      <link>/publication/stopify/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 15:39:56 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/stopify/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fission: Secure Dynamic Code-Splitting for JavaScript</title>
      <link>/publication/fission/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 17:19:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/fission/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
